<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>BeyondBasicsGuitar.com</title>
 <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com/"/>
 <updated>2016-12-04T12:07:40-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Paul Shumsky</name>
   <email>pshumsky@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Do I Have to Learn to Sight-Read?</title>
   <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//questions/2013/08/04/do-i-have-to-learn-to-sight-read"/>
   <updated>2013-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//questions/2013/08/04/do-i-have-to-learn-to-sight-read</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some of my guitar students question&lt;/strong&gt; whether learning to sight-read traditional music notation is important. It’s an interesting question. Guitar is probably one of the few instruments on which you can become really proficient without learning to read music, and many self-taught guitarists have gotten used to using tablature. However, becoming a decent sight-reader is beneficial in several ways that may not be readily apparent to the non-reader. For instance, in my teaching practice, one of my goals is to help you become a musician, not just a guitar player. I want you to be able to speak the language of music with pianists, horn players, bass players, drummers, etc. If you want the keyboard player in your band to work with the same piece of music, he will look at you cross-eyed if you hand him a piece of tablature to learn. There is nothing inherently wrong with TAB as a device for communicating how to finger a piece of guitar music, but that’s all it can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to sight-read reinforces many other skills you use as a fluent musician, and also provides these additional perks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Memorization of the fingerboard&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learning the fingerboard helps to quicken all music-making processes that require you to play the “right” notes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Musical fluency&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you become a proficient reader, you no longer read just one note, then the next note, etc. You notice groups of notes and automatically relate them to each other. For instance, you think to yourself: “Ahh, these notes constitute a Cmaj7 chord.” Or, “this measure contains a Dorian scale.” This ability to analyze and categorize as you read improves the quickness with which you can finger the notes. If you already know how to play the chord or scale you just analyzed, your fingers will jump to that place on the neck. Here’s a non-musical analogy: When you see a car driving down the road, you don’t think to yourself “C - A - R”, or “wheels, rims, fenders, bumper, hood, motor”, etc. You just perceive CAR, categorize it automatically and then interact with it, i.e. get out of its way or open the door without mulling it over!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Improves soloing&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe good sight-reading skills improves one’s soloing skills. It works like this: When sight-reading, the first thing you do is analyze the note or chord structure, then you find it on the fingerboard and play. When improvising, the first thing you do is listen to the melody in your head and then intuitively locate it on the fingerboard and play. It’s the same process - except the inspiration for the notes comes from your inner ear rather than a piece of sheet music. You still have to correctly analyze what it is you are reading or hearing in order to play it accurately. Thus, the better your sight-reading skills are, the faster you can translate your solo ideas to the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Improves the ability to jam and interact with others&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This time, the inspiration for what you play comes from the other players. As you listen to your bandmates play, you absorb the sound, analyze it and then interact with your own musical response. Again, many of the same skills used in interpreting written music are used here. Of course, ear training is another skill you are employing in this live situation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Provides an entry into the sheet music repertoire of all instruments&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you walk into a music store, there is suddenly a huge library of music available, and not just music written for guitar! Great music has been written for all instruments. Any instrument that uses the treble clef is the easiest to consider (e.g. brass, woodwinds, strings, keyboards). We guitarists have a smaller catalog available to us because composers did not start taking classical guitar seriously until the earlier part of the 20th century, at which time, master guitarist Andres Segovia encouraged composers to write compositions for guitar which he then championed around the world. Other instruments have centuries of repertoire available. As a proficient reader, you can take better advantage of it!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Who do you listen to?</title>
   <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2013/05/29/who-do-you-listen-to"/>
   <updated>2013-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2013/05/29/who-do-you-listen-to</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listening is a huge part&lt;/strong&gt; of developing musicianship. And listening to all kinds of music and instrumentalists, not just 
guitarists is very helpful. I have found over time as I have improved as a player, the music I have absorbed through
listening connects with something I’m practicing and helps my understanding. I myself am a music omnivore and like to
draw influences from many sources. Here are a few of my favorites that really turned my head as I was developing as a 
player. Feel free to respond with any albums that you love that have made an impact on your musical development…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jazz&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B000000Y27/qid=1071249747/sr=2-1/ref=sr_2_1/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;The Incredible Jazz Guitar of Wes Montgomery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Smokin-Half-Note-Wes-Montgomery/dp/B0006VXF4G/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1369253294&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=smokin+at+the+half+note&quot;&gt;Smokin’ At the Half Note - Wes Montgomery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000005BEK/ref=m_art_li_20/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Footprints - Pat Martino (orig. release title “The Visit”) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000000XIV/qid=1071252360/sr=1-1/ref=sr_1_1/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Portraits of Ellington - Joe Pass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0000262QW/ref=pd_bxgy_img_2/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Return to Forever - Chick Corea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B0000046YK/qid=1071252671/sr=2-1/ref=sr_2_1/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Light As a Feather - Chick Core with Return to Forever&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://http//www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B000002ADT/qid=1071513702/sr=2-1/ref=sr_2_1/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;Kind of Blue - Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt;  - read about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/programs/jazzprofiles/archive/miles_kob.html&quot;&gt;making of Kind Of Blue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B0000027GU/qid=1071513840/sr=2-2/ref=sr_2_2/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;Tribute to Jack Johnson - Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B00006GO9Q/qid=1071514405/sr=1-2/ref=sr_1_2/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;In a Silent Way - Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B00005B7RS/qid=1071515334/sr=2-1/ref=sr_2_1/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;Jazz Winds From a New Direction - Hank Garland (with a 17 year old Gary Burton!)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0000261L9/qid=1071521627/sr=1-1/ref=sr_1_1/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;Bright Size Life - Pat Metheny (with Jaco Pastorius and Bob Moses)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jazzguitar.dsl.pipex.com/TalFarlow/WithRedNorvo.htm&quot;&gt;Move! - Red Norvo (with Tal Farlow and a young Charles Mingus)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;World Music&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000003QJ3/qid=1071254061/sr=1-3/ref=sr_1_3/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Soro - Salif Keita&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000005H0F/qid=1071254541/sr=1-4/ref=sr_1_4/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Ni Kanu - Kante Manfila&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000000E2M/ref=m_art_li_1/104-6449218-9132766&quot;&gt;Super Soukous - Loketo with Diblo Dibala&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;(Diblo is considered by most to be the leading exponent of Zairean soukous guitar. Pretty neat stuff!)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rock&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000002P5W/qid=1071256087/sr=1-1/ref=sr_1_1/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Axis Bold as Love - Jimi Hendrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000002P5U/ref=pd_bxgy_img_2/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Electric Ladyland - Jimi Hendrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0000029W2/qid=1071258793/sr=1-36/ref=sr_1_36/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Bach Lute Works Vol. I - John Williams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0000028NJ/ref=pd_bxgy_img_2_cp/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Bach: The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book II - Glenn Gould, piano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B00005TZOE/qid=1071265204/sr=2-1/ref=sr_2_1/002-0048173-7078453&quot;&gt;Shamanic Dream - Anugama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Nylon or Steel</title>
   <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2013/01/21/nylon-or-steel"/>
   <updated>2013-01-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2013/01/21/nylon-or-steel</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; I want to buy my first guitar, should I buy one with nylon or steel strings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; Choosing a nylon or steel string guitar is an important decision. The nylon string guitar is really appropriate for classical music, but in my opinion, is not the right way to go for most other styles. It’s possible to play classical music on a steel string but steel strings do not have the flexibility or tonal range needed for serious classical right hand technique. Conversely, the sound produced by the nylon-stringed classical guitar is not what we associate with traditional popular styles such as folk, blues, jazz, rock, pop etc. Also, string bending techniques and fingerings common to pop music styles aren’t accessible on the wider classical fingerboard. So, you should buy a steel string folk guitar if you are mostly interested in popular styles and might want to dabble a bit in the classical realm, or buy a nylon string classical guitar if the reverse is true. I would not worry about whether steel or nylon strings are “easier” to play. I believe that idea to be a false concern.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do I have to use Alternate Picking?</title>
   <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//questions/2013/01/20/do-i-have-to-use-alternate-picking"/>
   <updated>2013-01-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//questions/2013/01/20/do-i-have-to-use-alternate-picking</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; You have asked me to practice “strict” alternate picking. Well, it seems that I have a habit of always using a down stroke when moving to a higher string (like 6 to 5) and an upstroke when moving to a lower string. Not sure where I picked this up but it is proving very difficult to change. I would rather not spend the time to un-learn this given all the new things I really want to work on. What are your thoughts on this? Is it critical for me to break this habit now? Will it lead to a roadblock later on if I don’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; The issue you mention is a common one with players just starting to build their technique. I believe strict alternate picking should be the primary picking style utilized. Although it may seem counter-intuitive to not just fall through the next string when crossing over, this creates problems with the “feel” of the playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We perceive music to have a natural downbeat and upbeat, just like when you tap your foot to music: the foot goes down, the foot goes up, etc. There is a natural emphasis on the downbeat and de-emphasis on the upbeat due to gravity. You are going against the natural order of things when you don’t use alternate picking. It is also very hard to play with a balanced, even sound and to develop speed when using an irregular picking pattern. There are times you might choose to use a “sweep picking” approach, but they require special left hand fingerings. You will need to slow your practicing way down to focus the necessary attention to change the habits you have ingrained. I highly recommend you say “down-up” out loud while practicing scales to facilitate the change. If you concentrate that way for a week or two, the habit should start to fall away. The sooner you are able to break the habit, the sooner you can start building a technique with a solid foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My Musical Genesis</title>
   <link href="http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2012/12/09/my-musical-genesis"/>
   <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://beyondbasicsguitar.com//2012/12/09/my-musical-genesis</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I was eight years old listening to the old tube radio next to my bed one evening when I heard this incredibly bright, energetic and fresh sound bursting from that six inch speaker that stopped my thoughts dead in their tracks. &lt;em&gt;Who is that?!&lt;/em&gt; I remember exclaiming to myself as I listened to the Beatles “I Want to Hold Your Hand” for the first time. It was over in two and a half electrifying minutes, so I turned the dial and found it on another station, and then another. After that night, I was hooked for life on the joy one can experience through music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My older brother Jeff had been playing guitar for a year or two and was really into the Hootenanny folk music that was popular then. I wanted a guitar but my parents said I had to prove that I was really interested so they gave me a ukulele for my eighth birthday. I learned some simple songs from books and it wasn’t long before I took it over to a friend’s house, taped a black toggle switch to the body to make it look like an electric guitar, and with my friend on snare drum, we would play along with the “Introducing the Beatles” Lp on Veejay Records. I stuck with that ukulele and on my 9th birthday, my parents came through with my first guitar, a used Harmony Sovereign folk guitar. Jeff taught me my first chords and a folk song called Sail Away by the Kingston Trio. A year later, I used paper route money to buy a used Harmony Rocket electric guitar and a no-name amplifier and actually spent considerable time in garages, jamming and learning licks and tunes with friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the Beatles, the Stones, and the rest of the British Invasion bands, over time my ears kept seeking new and visceral sounds. I starting listening to Paul Butterfield Blues Band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blues_Project&quot;&gt;The Blues Project&lt;/a&gt;, Cream, anything with good guitar lead, and emulating whatever I could. I didn’t find it easy, but I had a dogged fascination and interest that kept me hacking away. &lt;em&gt;How did they do it, how did he play that lick?&lt;/em&gt; It was the mystery of it all that fascinated me, and the first few times the light went on and I figured something out, and my fingers actually did what I commanded them to do, it was extremely satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to love this mysterious world where sound and expression could wash over me and transport me to a new reality. And once I arrived, I usually tried to play along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was 11, my parents signed me up to take a small jazz ensemble workshop with Chuck Mangione (he taught at the local Eastman School of Music). The other kids were quite a bit older than me but I passed the audition because I could play a blues progression with 9th chords, (although I didn’t know that’s what they were called!) Back then, by the way, Chuck had short hair and wore a suit. Through that class, I got my first up-close exposure to jazz and picked up some things by osmosis but my ears weren’t quite ready for that level of sophistication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my own speed, as I managed to understand one style, I needed more mystery to feed my habit. I had already graduated from folk and moved on to blues, electric blues and psychedelic rock. I was listening to the likes of Jimi Hendrix, Led Zeppelin, Derek and the Dominos, early Frank Zappa, Jean Luc Ponty, King Crimson, Pink Floyd, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_American_Metaphysical_Circus/&quot;&gt;Joe Byrd and the Field Hippies&lt;/a&gt;, and later, The Grateful Dead and the harmonized leads and rugged blues of early Allman Brothers. Walter Carlos’ Lp, “Switched-On Bach” became my first introduction to classical music and the amazing world of J.S. Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I was 15, my ears were beginning to mature. I was playing chord progressions that were more interesting than my barre chord jamming friends. My parents signed me up for my first real guitar lessons with Eastman student Jim Scott. Over the next six months, Jim introduced me to jazz chords and tunes like The Girl From Ipanema. (Jim later went on to spend many years with the Paul Winter Consort.) My love for harmonic mystery continued and I eventually found a pathway to jazz through the early jazz-rock fusion of Larry Coryell, John McLaughlin, Miles Davis and Chick Corea. It did not take long before I was seeking out straight-ahead jazz guitar masters like Kenny Burrell, George Benson, Wes Montgomery and Pat Martino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies with many great teacher/players came next, at New England Conservatory, Berklee College, Eastman School, gigs of all kinds, and an 11 year association with the world beat band Wildest Dreams where I discovered truly mystifying African rhythms and the amazing guitar artistry of African players like Diblo Dibala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was 15 and realized I had acquired some information about playing guitar that might be useful to others I have been teaching. There is nothing more satisfying for me than helping others explore the mystery of music and guitar and helping them find that light switch.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>